Hi, welcome. I'm Joanne
Donahue. I am an exercise
physiologist. I'm also a
nutritionist and I'm in the
Department of Osteopathic
Manipulative Medicine.
I have been at MYTCOM for
27 years, very long time.
I'm not a physician. My
area is nutrition and
exercise science. However,
I'm a director of clinical
research. So my research
over the last 25
years has all spanned
through exercise science,
nutrition, and rehabilitative
medicine, including
osteopathic manipulation.
So I have about one
hour today to get across
to you exercise science.
It's not enough nearly
to really get into depth
for it, but if there's
anything I hope you can get
out of this lecture
today, it's no matter what
field you pick with being
a physician that you
understand how exercise
science is applicable to that
field and just to understand
a little bit of how
our body response to
different exercises um and
how certain diseases and
things can impact on it
all right so getting
right into it here's your
session objectives i'm not
going to sit here and read
these to you so we're going
to go right on over and
you can actually um you
can go through and read
that i broke this up because
i know how you all have
zoom fatigue and video
fatigue so I'm going to break
this into sections and
go into the history of
exercise physiology then
we're going to touch on the
energy systems which a lot
of you from biochemistry
it will be a review but
how it applies to exercise
we're going to go into
how we measure exercise
intensity and why our
cardiovascular and pulmonary
adaptations to it muscle
fiber types and adaptations
exercise principles and at
the end I do have slides
with some clinical case
series and some slides of
guidelines for exercise
prescription that are based on
ACSM and the American
Heart Association. It's not
part of this lecture, but
the slides are at the end of
this, and I do want you to
know those for the test.
I'm not throwing any
tricks at you at the test.
It's just things that I don't
need to read off to you.
So starting this off,
the reason we started
this lecture, and I really
wish I could give a few of
these lectures, is years
ago, ACSM came out with
something. That's the American
College of Sports Medicine
called Exercises Medicine,
and it was really based
on a physician crisis.
Physicians were not asking
their patients enough about
their own physical activity.
They'll ask about their
diet. They ask about things,
but it's not something
that's typically heard of
in a routine exam. A little
bit more today, but what
the response back from
physicians was they were
not properly educated. They
didn't feel comfortable asking
about it. 85% of medical
schools did not educate on
exercise or nutrition, any
kind of behavioral counseling,
lifestyle modification,
and there really was no
preventative medicine. Now
osteopathic medicine is based
on that, but most medical
schools aren't. So in
response to this, they really
pushed this exercise as
medicine and wanted every
physician to ask about
exercise and prescribe exercise
by the year 2022 well that
didn't happen but we came
close we definitely made
a push for it but based on
research and this is fact
that I'm giving you right
now what we know is that
right now while you're in
medical school the habits
that you have for physical
activity will carry over to
as a physician if you are a
physician who's active you
are more likely to counsel
and prescribe exercise
and a healthy lifestyle to
your patients so if there's
anything that might you know
motivate you to get up
and move a little bit more
maybe this this would be
it and you could see on the
slide I have movement is
medicine because I kind of
changed what they said exercise
is medicine to movement
is medicine because I really
do believe movement is
medicine we've already showed
that you know you don't
have to get up and go to
a gym and work out for 45
minutes every morning but
just getting up and taking
small frequent breaks from
sitting is enough to improve
your vascular system. As
a matter of fact, if you
exercise and you still sit
for eight hours a day, they
show that it doesn't even
negate that. So I like to
look at it as movement,
getting people up and moving,
and everybody's in different
physical conditions. So
just kind of keep
that in mind when
you work with a
geriatric patient, that
movement is medicine
to many people.
So just briefly going
through what is exercise
physiology, it's the study
of how the body response to
physical activity. Physical
activity is relative to
every individual. Someone
who just came out of surgery,
just getting up and going
to a bathroom is going
to be exhausting. It's going
to be enough to trigger
a very high physical
activity response in them.
We look at the
intricate changes in
metabolism,
cardiovascular function,
muscular systems,
respiratory processes
before, during,
and after exercise.
guys. This slide is
just to show you how far
we have come. I love
this slide. It makes me
laugh so much. In 1904,
the winner of the Olympic
marathon was Tom X. Hicks.
He was an accountant
and that's his friends
were accountants
next to him carrying him
after the race because
he won the marathon in
three hours and 28 minutes
for the Olympics. Now,
for those of you who
follow, you know that
that's a decent time but
that's not anywhere close
to winning a marathon
in comparison in 2022 the
olympic winner came in
and in two hours and five
minutes now we can say
that we breed superhumans
but physiologically we
have not changed which
changes our knowledge of how
the human body functions
and how we work and how
we've made ourselves so
much more efficient now
the scope of what people
think exercise science is
is predominantly what
you see in the first box
here, focusing on optimizing
athletic performance,
reducing injuries, especially
in competitive athletes,
and minimizing any kind of
complications that go along
with, you know, overuse
injuries and things like that.
However, this lecture is
going to be more about your
clinical exercise physiology,
and this is what you're
going to see as physicians
more, especially what you
see in that image. It's going
to be more of emphasizing
therapeutic applications
for disease management,
cardiovascular and pulmonary
rehabilitation, and improving
quality of life in a various
degree of populations.
When we move, we cannot move
without everything single
system taking part in it.
If something goes wrong with
one system in our body,
it's going to impact how we
have performed physical
activity so we know that through
the musculoskeletal system
that we have sarcomeres
and they power through their
microscopic contractions
that contain actin and myosin
filament they slide past
each other during muscle
contraction they generate force
and movement but they
couldn't do that if we didn't
have a proper cardiovascular
system they couldn't do
that if we didn't have a
proper respiratory system and
even that being said our nervous
system can't work properly
yet if there's something
wrong with our nervous
system and we have neurological
conditions if anybody's
gone to our rock steady
boxing program you understand
that it's a neurological
condition and they have problems
moving because of their
problems moving and their
difficulties moving they have
issues with cardiovascular
disease they have issues
with musculoskeletal weakness
and function so we're all
this amazing unit put together
where everything kind of
feeds off of each other.
And we all feed off of it by
one thing, ATP, ATP, every
single movement from
blinking to deadlifting, we
require energy, but our body
does not store a lot of ATP.
Um, so therefore we have
different energy systems
and it all depends on
what we need our energy
for. I mean, right now
you're sitting and you're
watching this. You don't
need a lot of energy just
to sit and watch a video,
but if I got up and I
told you we're going to
all sprint together for 10
seconds well we need
immediate energy so how do
we reproduce and replenish
ATP energy well it's
our three systems you have
your phosphagen system
glycolysis and your
oxidative phosphorylation so
your phosphagen system
is instant it's immediate
it's explosive movements
you don't need oxygen
it's anaerobic completely
and it's limited by
the amount of creatine
phosphate that we store
creatine phosphate when
you have fast twitch fibers
we store more of it and if
you have slow twitch you
don't store as much of
it we are all born with a
set amount of type one and
type two fibers and we're
going to go into that a
little bit later but think
of your phosphagen system
as your emergency generator
okay it's that first 10
seconds sprinting you know
getting away from what
you need to get away from.
And it relies on the stored
ATP and the creatine phosphate.
Now, as we move into
it, the next few
seconds, we have
glycolysis. Okay.
Again, short term
up to 90 seconds.
It's anaerobic
breakdown of glucose.
It produces lactate as a
byproduct and it's limited
by this acid base. And we're
going to go into lactic
acid in the next slide.
And then anything longer
than those like two minutes,
roughly 90 seconds, two
minutes. Um, now you're
going into your oxidative
phosphorylation system and
we use glucose and fats
for this. And I have proteins
written in there, but
you really do not tap into
your protein stores, um,
muscles until about 90
minutes of exercise with no
energy stores left, which
is why anybody who does
endurance training after
a certain amount of time,
we always replenish our
energy stores because we
don't want to deplete our
stores and go into muscle
breakdown, gluconeogenesis.
But also that can happen
in someone who's also an
anorexic or in starvation
mode, or if we miss that
balance between, you
know, consuming enough
calories and exercise. Your
phosphagen system, as I
stated before, you have type
two fast twitch fibers,
which contain much higher
levels of creatine phosphate
than your type one, which
you're slow twitch, you're
oxidative. I call them
the prius of your energy
because it's slow and steady
but it's also a um I had
a little shifting gear
on there because I always
think of the human body as
as a stick shift car not
that anybody drives stick
shift anymore a few of you
might but you have your
first your second third
fourth fifth gear and with
that being said um you're
not just shifting from one
gear to the the other ones
are always in the background
so when we deplete that
quick 10 second 20 seconds
of energy and then we move
into our aerobic system
that gives the aerobic
system time to replenish that
which is why all of a
sudden someone can sprint
be fatigued walk slowly and
then sprint again because
we're replenishing that
creatine phosphate is probably
the most studied supplement
on the market today
i'm not a huge fan of
supplements i i think that um
there's very little guidance
on them and when you take
too much of something you
usually become deficient in
something else however
creatine phosphate has a lot of
positive research out there
on it so that's why you'll
see people especially
bodybuilders or sprinters they'll
take creatine phosphate
as a supplement but it's
actually also been shown
in geriatric populations
neurological populations to
help with energy as well so all
of them studied out there
and it's taken all different
ways but again with anything
else, if you take too much
of something, it's just
going to be excreted out. So
if you do decide that
you're going to supplement
something or you're going to
tell a patient to take it,
make sure you know the guidelines
and how much they should
be taking for their body
weight because it differs
for everybody.
So if oxygen is available
in our system, pyruvate
enters the mitochondria
to fuel Krebs cycle.
If not, and oxygen
is not available, and
we are working
anaerobically with our
other systems, it's
converted into lactate.
It'll ask glycolysis to
continue even without oxygen.
However,
like sprinting or
things like that,
anything more than
a few seconds,
you're going to eventually
change the pH because
lactic acid starts to
build up. And once we
start building up lactic
acid and the pH changes
it leads to an increase
in hydrogen ions and we
don't have a balance
anymore we try to expel
those hydrogen ions by
expelling carbon dioxide
to get rid of that but
once we don't keep up with
that balance we go into
something called metabolic
acidosis and this is that
burning sensation that
you feel when you're
lifting a weight too many
times and you're burning
and you can't pick that
muscle up anymore and
you're fatigued or if we're
running and we're sprinting
and we are fatigued
that's your peripheral
fatigue that's metabolic
acidosis that's our body
not clearing hydrogen ions
so this is just a quick
summary slide of all of the
systems put into one thing
which one's working when um
and and the minute system so
just be familiar with this
this is my little
break and pause because
i love to do this
true or false um Um,
this, this drives me
insane when I hear
this at the gym,
you only burn fat in
a fat burning zone
at low intensity.
Um,
I think I probably just
gave you the answer the
way I just said that,
but the answer is false.
Um, that's not, that's
not correct. And there's
a lot of terminology
that's thrown around in
exercise science that as
physicians and scientists,
you really need to change
the way you say it.
while we do burn fat
as you're sitting here
watching this you're
burning fat predominantly
so at a lower intensity
you're using predominantly
fat as your energy source
you burn more calories
when you're in a moderate
to high intensity zone
using glucose because
glucose burns more calories
plus when you work at a
higher intensity and you're
burning higher your body
has to recover That's called
EPOC, excess post-oxygen
consumption, and the
afterburn, and that burns
more calories. So when someone
says you should work for
this slow amount of time
and this fat burning,
it's not necessarily true.
And it could be very
misleading for people depending
on what their goals are with
weight loss or training.
All right, so how do we
measure systems that we're
working on? No, that's not
my cat, but I have three
cats, and I didn't know what
to put on this page, and
I thought it was cute, so
I put a cat on the page.
We have so many ways of
measuring exercise intensity.
The biggest one that
everybody knows is heart rate,
and it's so easy to collect
heart rate now. We have so
many amazing tools. We have
an iWatch. We have heart
rate straps. We even have
wearables now that you can
wear shirts that measure
heart rate. uh that thing on
your finger that you see
there that they actually even
do that now for um sleep
apnea it actually measures
your oxygen um it measures
your pulse oxen your heart
rate throughout the night
and instead of actually going
to a lab it measures all
of that during the night
and can test for that so
heart rate heart rate reserve
is always our go-to and
easiest way of doing it we
also have something called
a rate of perceived exertion
and that's the borg scale
that you see on this scale
right here. We use this in
research. We use this during
exercise testing. It is
a validated scale that
basically we just ask you, do
you feel like you're working
extremely light, very
light, light, somewhat hard?
Believe it or not, this
scale does actually correlate
with heart rate zones.
That's why it's a validated
scale. And then the gold
standard is oxygen consumption.
Oxygen consumption is the
only way it really can
be recorded is through
indirect calorimetry which
is the machine that you see
up there and I will show
it to you on the next
slide and that's really
where it also can measure
our ventilatory threshold.
So indirect calorimetry
is maximum oxygen
uptake is how we measure
it and what it is
is the maximum amount
of oxygen that you can
utilize during intense
maximal exercise.
To get a true maximal
test there's so many other
limiting factors to max
exercise when people
say it. In the video that
you see here, we have
this in our lab in the
clinic. We also have one
in another building in
our exercise science lab.
We do testing all the time
on various populations.
So if anybody would
like to watch a test or
do research, I do research
a lot with this test.
It is the best way of
measuring it. However,
that's your respiratory
system. If I was to test you
on a cycle like you see
in the picture on the man
on the left right there we
have limiting factors to
maximal oxygen consumption
there because muscular
fatigue will set in prior
on a treadmill we don't have
the muscular fatigue on a
treadmill on a bicycle we
have to produce power with
our legs to move it so we
always assume your vo2 max
on a bike is going to be
lower than if we tested it
on a treadmill and that's
why our modality changes and
if we're testing somebody
who's in a wheelchair and
we have to use an upper
body ergometry, we have
much smaller muscles and
we don't have the capacity
to produce as much oxygen.
So VO2 max changes with
the modality that we change
it at. We also have portable
ones like you can see
in the picture here. And
this is how we measure it.
How this works is we know
what ambient air is. Air is
20% oxygen, 0.03 carbon
dioxide nitrogen. So while
you're on this machine it's
not um you can set it if this
is called indirect there
is something called direct
calorimetry where we could
actually change the bariatric
pressure to make it almost
simulate altitude exercise
but for the most part
what we're doing is you're
breathing in room air and what
it's doing is measuring what
you're um exhaling so based
on what you're inhaling
the changes in your exhaled
carbon dioxide and oxygen
is reflecting your ongoing
metabolism during exercise.
So I promise this is the only
formulas I will put
on here for you.
Also with carbon dioxide
and oxygen, the exchange
of that is called your
respiratory exchange ratio.
So the ratio of carbon
dioxide expired per minute
as compared to the volume
of oxygen consumed per
minute is your respiratory
exchange ratio, just
as you see here. And what
it does, it indicates
would fuel the body is
using. So in other words,
if we are burning carbohydrates,
we have six oxygen
here, we have six carbon
dioxide here. What
this does in the highlighted
here is it's an even
respiratory exchange of
oxygen to carbon dioxide.
However, if we are doing
oxidation of a fatty
molecule, fatty acid,
and this brings us back
to what I said before,
that carbohydrates are
slightly different when
it comes to burning
fatty acids. So with
fatty acids, we have 23
oxygen molecules as opposed
to 16 carbon dioxide
molecules. And that's when
you do the math with this,
our exchange comes down to
0.7. So what does that mean
to us when we do a test
on somebody? If somebody,
respiratory exchange ratio,
when I hook them up to
this machine and they are
0.7, I know that they're
mostly at a resting state.
They're at a very low state.
They're burning mostly fat,
low intensity exercise.
Once they climb up
towards one, I know that
they're burning more
carbohydrates, more
anaerobic, and they're
probably getting to a more
intense exercise. So
this number is really
important when we use
it for testing. With
that being said, we know
what fuel is being burned
so I can actually see how
much calories someone's
burning so again I promise
this is the last math I will
show you on here for
equations we know that there's
5.05 kcals per liter of
oxygen consumed because
carbohydrates are more oxygen
efficient they give more
energy per unit. Okay. Now,
if we have fat catabolism,
that yields 4.73 calories
per liter of oxygen.
Fat requires more oxygen
to break down. So it's
less efficient in terms
of calories per liter.
So your real world
application here is this
formula below. Let's say
we have someone of the
same height, weight, and
they are running, um,
for 30 minutes on a treadmill.
Okay. So we know per
minute that they're burning
per liter of oxygen that
if they're at a low if
they're working at a low
intensity if they're in
their um quote fat zone that
people say that you should
stay in we know if they're
burning more fat they're
burning 4.73 calories per
liter of of um per minute
so that's seven calories per
minute for 30 minutes
they're burning 212 calories
however if they're working
a little bit harder for
those 30 minutes and they're
burning more carbohydrates
because they're in a higher
heart rate zone they're
working at a higher intensity
they're burning at 5
.505 calories per minute and
that's 7.6 for 30 minutes
so they're burning 228 calories
so you burn more calories
now is that an earth
-shattering number no but i
just wanted to prove the
point that when you are in a
higher zone, you are burning
more calories and staying
in that low zone. So if
you're trying to lose fat,
a caloric deficit matters
more than burning fat
as fuel. And what I mean
by caloric deficit is
your diet. Diet is
predominantly responsible for
any kind of weight loss. So
moderate to high intensity
workouts, not only does
it burn more calories, but
it actually builds more
mitochondria and it helps with
your efficiency. And we'll
go into that in a second.
So what affects your max
VO2? A lot of things, a lot,
a lot, a lot of things
affects your VO2. Your size,
women, your gender, women
tend to are smaller. We
have less body composition.
We have less hemoglobin,
which allows less oxygen
carrying capacity so women
will always have a lower vo2
max um that has that's not
being said about anaerobic
threshold which we'll go
into genetics again remember
i said we were all born
with your muscle fiber types
and i will probably say
this a few times in this
lecture but when we are born
with type 2 and type 1
fibers we can make type 2
fibers have more oxidative
properties to be like type
1 fibers but you cannot
make type 1 fibers oxidative
fibers become more type 2
properties and faster hence
why they say speed is really
you're born with speed
if you want to increase
your speed um you're either
born with it or you're
not and if you're going to
increase it it usually comes
down to mechanics efficiency
and um but but not changing
your muscle fiber type
so other things that affect
it are oxidative enzymes,
your AVO2 difference.
We're going to get to that
in a second. Your cardiac
output, your altitude that
you're at affects it. Air
quality. I don't think I have
it on there. Air quality
is big. Sometimes we hear
that air quality index is
high, majorly affects it.
The quantity of muscles
activated for the type
of exercise. Remember I
talked about modality.
If you're on a bike or
if you're a swimmer and I
test you on a treadmill,
you're not going to do
as well as if I tested
you in the water. So all
these things play a
factor into your VO2 max.
Before I go into
it, I just want you
to see what it looks
like on a test.
So as we exercise, the
blue line is your oxygen.
Okay, so exercise intensity
is going up. This is your
power watts on a bike.
We're pedaling hard, hard,
hard. Here's your blue
line. Your red line is your
carbon dioxide.
So we see here it increases
linearly with exercise
as it should. but right
about here we see that
it actually crosses over
and this spot right here
is what we call our anaerobic
threshold. It's where
we have gone from using
oxygen as our source of
energy to being anaerobic
and this plays a major
role in how we do rehab
for so many populations.
We'll get to that
on your next slide
because we have other
things to consider
ventilation so at rest
we breathe about 12 to 25
times per minute we
never think about
it it's not anything
we think about
and it's just for basic needs
but as exercise increases
our breathing rate increases
gradually and it rises
in sync with our oxygen
consumption and work light
but here's where it gets really
interesting with exercise
so at around a 60 percent
of your maximal capacity
or at about like 40 50 percent
and less trained people
this linear relationship
changes so all of a sudden
your vo2 will max out but
then your ventilation and
you start the breathing starts
to climb much more rapidly
and that's because you've
hit your maximum your
lung capacity and you're
not getting enough air into
your system so now you start
to breathe more rapidly
because we're trying to
compensate for that and again
this comes this inflection
point is called your ventilatory
threshold. And your
ventilatory threshold is very
similar to your anaerobic
threshold. It's when everything
kind of just changes
system. It marks when your
body begins relying on
anaerobic metabolism. It's when
we start producing lactate
and carbon dioxide more.
So it stimulates us
breathing more because
we're trying to exhale
more carbon dioxide to get
rid of the hydrogen
ions. So I'm just going
to show you this is the
grasp of what ventilation
looks like. All of
a sudden it goes up
linearly with carbon
dioxide and then it spikes.
But we're going to put this all
together in one giant picture.
So with this graph, and
so we already know, here's
your red line. Your red line
is carbon dioxide. Your blue
line is oxygen consumption.
Boom, boom, boom. It's
all going linearly. Now
your green line right here.
Again, everything's working.
That's your ventilation.
Everything's working perfectly,
perfectly, perfectly.
Now all of a sudden, right
where that line is, we start
to see that's where a
major shift happens. Okay,
so we look at a few factors
for this, and this is called
your anaerobic threshold
or ventilatory threshold.
This is where if someone
who is an athlete wants to
improve in performance, I
say, okay, what's your heart
rate at this point? This
is where we need to train.
Now, if you're dealing with
a disease population, we
look at other thresholds.
We look at this for lactic
acid. We look at this for
claudication pain and I will
show you in the next few
slides again what that looks
like and down here by the
way this is your respiratory
exchange ratio it fluctuates
between 0.7 and 1.0 which
is why you won't see it too
much of an inflection on
this graph but when I'm testing
somebody I'm simultaneously
looking at all these
numbers moving in real time
I can tell when someone
is hitting peak exercise
before they can I will ask
them how they're doing how
they're doing great great
great great i have it down to
within two minutes i know
if someone's going to say oh
my gosh get me off and jump
off the treadmill because
this is just what happens
with our whole system let's
talk about your
lactic acid anaerobic
threshold kind of
simultaneously right
to test lactate um what i
what i was showing was your
anaerobic threshold through
the ventilatory threshold
through our metabolics um
lactate is measured through
our blood and it's very
simple test it's a finger
stick that we either do with
someone while they're on
the treadmill a finger stick
or out in the field with
a finger stick or we sometimes
do it like you see in
the picture there with
the ear very simple almost
looks like a glucometer very
simple to test um but it's
unpleasant um some people
find finger sticks more
painful than blood draws I
do so it's not like we always
want to stick somebody um
with it but the reason I
have this on here with the
lactate threshold and I have
Lance Armstrong on there
and some of you might be too
young to remember Lance
Armstrong but he won the
Tour de France a few times
and then he was really shamed
because he was um he had
all his titles taken away
from him for blood doping
but before that happened um
the reason he was we all
thought that he was this
amazing person that had this
ability to just have this um
he always excelled at the
hills when he was in the
Tour de France because he
had a very high lactic acid
threshold. While most people
increased their intensity
in the hills and built
this lactic acid and had to
reduce their intensity, he
increased it. He did it. He
was taking a drug called
EPO, which it does. What it
does is it increases your
red blood cell count. When
you increase your red blood
cell count, it's increasing
your oxygen carrying
capacity. So this indirectly
improves your lactic acid
threshold. So this is
one way when you see
athletes, when they say
they're blood doping this
is what they mean and it
definitely puts them at
an advantage um so it's
basically performance
handing because the concept
behind it it's performance
and handing because
it's improving your oxygen
availability so your
muscles rely less on
anaerobic metabolism with
athletes when we look
athlete one is in red athlete
two is in blue we look at
the red their lactic acid
threshold is at eight miles
per hour on the treadmill
whereas the first second
athletes it's at six miles
per hour six and a half miles
per hour on the treadmill
so even though their vo2
max if we did a vo2 max
test was kind of similar
the person that's going to
be able to work out harder
and faster is the person
who has a higher lactic acid
threshold so this is really
trying to cut this i'm
trying to put a picture in
your head with athletes
because when we're dealing
with a diseased population
it's not much different
than this so we're going to
put this all together now.
Okay. So now we have
heart rate that increases.
The red line is oxygen that's
increasing. The blue line
is, I mean, sorry, red line
is your carbon dioxide,
blue line. So we know
ventilation all increasing. What
I want you to focus on here
is the maroon line because
that's your lactic acid.
That's the blood. So we
can see here, it all kind
of happens around the same
area we see a spike in
ventilation we see a spike in
blood lactate we see the
crossover of carbon dioxide
exceeding oxygen and we have
a heart rate here and this
is how we prescribe exercise
we say okay now we have a
clinical interpretation of
where this person should
be training at they should
be training at a heart rate
at probably about 160 to
170 and that would really
train them harder and build
that lactic acid threshold.
Now let's take this with
a diseased population.
Let's take it with somebody
who has angina pain. When
we test them on this machine,
we see all of this, but
let's see we start to
see on the cardiogram ST
depression right about here,
or we see that they start to
have angina pain right
about here. Obviously, we
terminate the test when that
happens but now we know that's
our threshold the same as
an anaerobic threshold now
we know when they are in
cardiac rehab that we are
going to work them right up
to that point why because
we want them to build
collateral vessels and we want
the body to adapt to that and
include and increase their
perfusion we want to increase
their av02 difference
in their cardiac output
which we will get to in the
next few slides desaturation
and dyspnea we have
something called a dyspnea
scale it's a very simple scale
plus one plus two plus
three plus four when someone
tells us they're out of breath
at a plus three plus four
because they're desaturating
down to maybe 90 oxygen
saturation we stop the test
and we say okay if that
happens right we're here
now we know what heart rate
that they're at we know
that the heart rate's at 125
we know this is when they
start to desaturate. So when
we go to pulmonary rehab,
we say, okay, let's work
them up into this point and
we bring them back again.
The reason being is we cannot
cure COPD. We cannot cure
chronic obstructive
pulmonary disease, but we can
make them more efficient.
And by more efficient, what
I mean is we can get them to
rely on less oxygen possibly
at a lower level. We can
get them to walk further.
We can build collateral
vessels and we can improve
their AVO2 difference, which
is how we extract oxygen.
So doing these tests in a
diseased population allows
us to have a clinical picture
of where to work them.
Claudication pain,
peripheral vascular disease,
same thing. When someone's
walking, their calf
muscles are killing. If
you've ever seen someone
walk on a treadmill with
peripheral pain, it's
awful to watch. And keep
in mind, People who take
statin drugs, it's
extremely, extremely common.
Statin drugs inhibit
glycolysis, and people
who take statin drugs
for cholesterol, it's
probably their number one
complaint if they don't
take CoQ10 with it.
When they start walking
or exercising, they
complain of muscle pain.
It still upsets me
when physicians do not
prescribe CoQ10 with
that because it's not in
their head. They're not
making it up. It's limiting
their exercise capacity
due to the inhibition
of glycolysis because
of the medication.
So that's why we do this
exercise testing, not just
in athletes, but we do it
in diseased population.
All right, let's take
a break for one second.
Here's a little fact
that I get all the time.
You can't build
muscle and lose fat
at the same time.
True or false?
I mean, in a perfect
world, we all want
to lose fat and build
muscle, correct?
Um,
it's true. Okay.
If someone is not trained,
this is very specific and
I want to be very clear
about this. It's possible,
especially for beginners. And
you're going to see this a
lot with GLP one people who
are taking GLP one medications
because usually people
who are taking these GLP
one medications are very
overweight or they have diabetes
and usually live a
sedentary lifestyle so if we
beginners and those or those
returning from a long break
with good nutrition and
adequate protein you probably
can hold on to the muscle
you have while losing fat
however if you're a highly
trained athlete or you're
trying to do something
anybody who is a bodybuilder
knows how difficult it
is to lose that fat while
maintaining muscle people
who do competitions for
bodybuilding what they put
themselves to do for this to
lose fat and build muscle
for competition is not
sustainable it's just
something that's done prior to
and they'll tell you it's
not sustainable you're going
to lose if someone's losing
quite a bit of weight
regardless if you're
lifting weights and taking
enough protein you
probably will lose a
little bit of muscle our
goal is to hold on to
as much muscle as we can
while we lose the fat
moving on to cardiac output
we just went through the
lungs the ventilatory system
how we breathe in and out
on this test um now we're
going to look at cardiac
output because now we have the
heart that has to take this
amazing oxygen in blood
and pump it to the rest of
all our vessels and how does
this impact on us right so
cardiac output i know you
are like i think you've all
had cardiology at this point
um is your heart rate how
many times your heart beats
um with how much blood it
pumps out your stroke volume
how much is coming out
of that left ventricle okay
in a healthy adult you usually
cardiac output is about
four and a half to five and
a half liters per minute
during maximal exercise that
can actually go to 20 liters
per minute depending on
your training status but
if you take someone who has
heart failure um who might
have a reduced ejection
fraction but their stroke
volume um is significantly
diminished due to systolic
function um your cardiac output
is limited and it won't
rise adequately in exercise
and you will see this very
rapidly on an exercise with
any kind of exertion they
will exhibit fatigue and and
poor exercise tolerance
right away but if you have
someone in heart failure
whose ejection fraction
remains normal but the
diastolic filling is impaired
um stroke volume can be
fixed or blunted um but
the heart rate can't
increase because your cardiac
output is just under stress
um this can explain why
sometimes people with
heart failure they can
actually appear stable at
rest and but once you do
anything with exertion
with them they can quickly
decompensate with activity
but factors affecting your
cardiac output or your
sympathetic nervous system
adrenaline so there's two
different types of this um
i work with esport athletes
a lot and someone put a
paper out that said that
they have increased heart
rate and so it's considered
exercise and nothing upset
me more because that's
the sympathetic nervous
system it's epinephrine so
if i jump at you and i scare
you yes your heart rate
goes up but it's not that's
your sympathetic nervous
system that's increasing it
um it's not continuous
exercise that's increasing
blood flow and working
muscles. It's very different.
But the things that
affect your cardiac output
obviously is your blood
volume, how much is flowing
through you. I always
love to look at this as
hoses and pipes in the
piping system in your house,
how much it's pumping
out and how much stroke
volume is coming out of that
faucet and how many times
you turn that faucet on
is the cardiac output.
But let's talk about
things that impact this.
your cardiac response to
exercise so there's factors
that affect your heart
rate so if your heart
rate's affected like let's
say you are on a beta
blocker it's going to affect
your cardiac output your
stroke volume might be
fine but if your heart
rate's lower and your
stroke volume stays the same
it's going to still reduce
your cardiac output same
thing with this if your
heart rate stays the same
but we increase your
stroke volume you're going
to increase your cardiac
output. So one is, is
really has, if you can't
impact cardiac output, um,
with one without the
other. So if heart rate's
affected, it's impacted. If
stroke volume is affected,
your cardiac output is,
is impacted by exercise.
Concentric versus eccentric
ventricular hypertrophy.
So we adapt to exercise.
Um, all my bodybuilders
right now are going to
get really mad at me.
there's a preload on your
heart when we do cardiovascular
okay and preload refers
to the volume of blood
returning to the heart it's
the end diastolic volume
and it stretches that left
ventricle before contraction
and it makes it really
strong when it stretches
the ventricle out think
of a balloon when you keep
if you put a balloon under
a faucet at full speed
and it stretches that balloon
out um and it's a brand
new balloon and then you
you're going to contract act
it out. Eventually that
balloon is going to stretch
out if you keep putting
that much force into it,
right? But it's still
keeping the properties, that
elastic property. So it's
actually really good. It makes
it larger and it actually
makes it again so that
your cardiac output is more
because you're increasing
your stroke volume with
that preload on the heart.
Then you have the afterload.
Now your afterload is
the resistance that the left
ventricle faces to push it
out of the heart so in
contrast it has to pump against
it so if you have high
blood pressure or if your
vessels are stiff and not
elastic that's putting a back
load on it that means
your heart has to push a
little harder to get it out
now why with strength training
is this an issue we do
something called a valsal
maneuver a lot in strength
training we're constantly
tensing and when we contract
we're tightening up the
vessels and when we do
that we're putting a stress
against the heart. We're
putting an afterload and what
this does time after time
if it's done repeatedly is
it creates eccentric hypertrophy
in the left ventricle
which means it's a thickening
of the muscle. So the
chamber gets smaller. The
muscle thickens and it can
be strong but you're not
getting as much blood in
there because you're making
the wall thicker. So the
chronic preload is actually
great with the cardiovascular,
the volume overload, but
when we have too much
resistance training, it can
thicken it and lower it.
Also, it puts a lot of stress
on the valves because the
valves have that constant
pressure that they're going
against and it can lead
to aortic valve narrowing.
Hence, what's the bodybuilder
that I'm thinking of
Arnold Schwarzenegger. Arnold
Schwarzenegger had to have
a valve replacement. It's
very common in bodybuilders
if it's their career and in
lifelong training to have
valve replacements because
of that constant afterload.
So this is just a
diagram to know and
kind of help you
understand it more of
how the volume is
squeezing in and out.
Understand that these are
medical conditions that can
decrease your stroke volume.
There are a lot of things
out there, but these are
things that you can really
pick up on, especially
with an echocardiogram. So
these are conditions that
decrease stroke volume, so
understand those. And then
we're going to talk about the
AVO2 difference, arteriovenous
oxygen difference.
And this is, again, something
that affects our exercise
performance. So when we
talk about oxygen delivery
and utilizing it, now we of
the heart pumping all this
blood out during exercise
when we focus on it though
we have to know how much
of that oxygenated blood is
actually being extracted
from the tip from the tissues
and that difference in
oxygen between the arterial
and venous blood flow is
called your av02 difference
and it's about five millimeters
of oxygen per hundred
millimeters of blood and it
can ride up to 15 million
meters when you're going
more don't worry about those
numbers i'm not going to ask
those to you um but oxygen
extraction to the working
muscles and it's really
dependent on muscle fiber
type so type one your slow
twitch ones are rich in
mitochondria because they're
oxygenated um they use oxygen
and myoglobin so they're
very oxidative and they're
they're very efficient at
extracting this so they dominate
in endurance athletes and
they're responsible for a
very large av02 difference
seen during prolonged
aerobic activity type two um
especially the type 2x they
reload on anaerobic so they
have a very much smaller
contribution to the av02
difference um again in patients
with heart failure that
perfusion and that mitochondrial
dysfunction you have
both blunted oxygen delivery
and extraction so training
them um to improve mitochondrial
density and capitalization
and shifting the way
their fibers recruit is
also a bonus when we do cardiac
rehab with these patients
so it's not just um it's a
it's a really good marker
of muscle oxidative capacity
and training status. But
this also is affected by
altitude and other factors.
So things that increase
your ABO2 difference on this
one, I'm going to ask
you just go back and look
at it just for the sake of
time because I only have
a few more minutes to get
this to you. So when you
see these tables on here,
please just go back and
just understand which diseases
do increase. Now remember
this, pay attention
to the arrows up there
increases it and then I have
a table that also shows what
decreases it okay and these
are all again clinically
clinical ways that
decrease it we're going to
talk about extreme
temperatures now and how that
impacts on on exercise so
this image that you see here
this is the picture of
the 2022 Olympics in Tokyo
that is the finish line of
the triathlon where most
athletes collapsed and
these are highly trained the
top athletes in the world
and why did they collapse
and really heat and humidity
now the temperature was
86.9 degrees fahrenheit
that day 30.5 for those of
you who are using celsius
and from overseas now 86
.9 we go that's hot but is
that really enough to make
people collapse but what
we're looking at now is
relative humidity and what
happens to the body. So,
um,
if the temperature, um, if
the air temperature is a
hundred degrees Fahrenheit
and the relative humidity is
15%, the heat index is 96
degrees Fahrenheit. That
means what your body is
perceiving that. Okay. So it's
almost lower. So even though
the temperature, you know,
people say a dry heat,
there is something to a dry
heat and a moist heat, that's
a dry heat. However, if
we look at what the heat
index is, this tells you what
it really feels like with
humidity. Why? Because with
humidity, we have, it
reduces our sweat evaporation
when we have high humidity.
So the body is not able to
cool itself. So the core
temperature rises. This means
all the blood is going to
our, I showed you on the
last slides, I just want
to go back to it. It shows
you most of our blood is
going to the skin. Okay. So
it's being redirected. So when
we look at this now, nobody
ever pays attention. We
all hear it on the radio.
Oh, it's going to feel like
it's 80 degrees, but it's
going to feel like 110.
Well, there is truth to that.
And this tells you why.
If the temperature is 86
degrees outside, like it was
for that marathon, but it's
90% humidity to our body,
it's 105 degrees heat
index. That's what the heat
index means and if you are
a physician who's overseeing
a race or you have to
make a call on events
understanding this obviously is
vital and it will tell you
when it's dangerous and
why because the higher the
humidity the more the time
to exhaustion so your
blood gets shunted to your
skin so what does that mean
it means that you have less
blood going to the working
muscles you dehydrate
more rapidly um you have a
decreased stroke volume you
have a decreased cardiac
output because the blood
is not being pumped there
it's going there and your
perceived exertion is much
higher so it makes moderate
exercise feel even harder
at moderate temperatures
so high humidity it really
dangerously elevates the
physiological strain which
was we saw in the olympics
there and we've seen it
in marathons i think las
vegas had a marathon once
where they ran out of water
and they had a medical
emergency where ambulance
were coming because the heat
index was just too high.
So that's one area of how
VO2 and exercise can be
impacted by the elements.
Let's go to the other
extreme. This is a heart
-wrenching story a few years
ago, three years ago, I
think it was. This was an
ultramarathon in China where
they were doing a 62-mile
event up in the mountains,
a very popular race.
And what happened in a very
short period of time, the
weather changed drastically
and 21 of the top
competitors died due to high
winds and to hypothermia.
They were too far out and
rescue workers couldn't get
them. So this is another
extreme. Now, it is not
dangerous to exercise in
cold weather until a certain
extreme. And actually, when
you exercise in the cold,
it's not bad. It actually
can increase your metabolic
rate until we get to a certain
point. And this is where
we see the weather center
with the windchill chart
so when we hear that
temperatures fall below zero
that's fine but with the
windchill we always hear with
the windchill i went to
school near canada we used to
hear the windchill all
the time would be minus 25
degrees you can't go on a
chairlift you can't walk to
class so when you hear that
um again this will affect
it because you have
vasoconstriction now and you're not
going to get the proper um
blood flow and you actually
have to worry about more
hypothermia during this
so this chart is just why
vo2 max decreases in extreme
weather just know like i
said if i have a chart on
here go back look at it know
your charts on here that
being said why do cardiac
events occur when people
shovel snow there's this
is kind of like the perfect
storm and if you ask any
physician who's ever been in
the emergency room they'll
tell you when a snowstorm
occurs they all go uh-oh
all hands on deck during a
snowstorm why one you have
cold induced vasoconstriction
so the temperature causes
your blood vessels to
constrict that raises your
blood pressure when you are
shoveling snow you're
increasing the workload on your
heart as well so now you
have vasoconstriction while
you're performing a
cardiovascular exercise your
blood becomes less viscous
it's cold out so now we have
a reduced blood flow now
you're doing strenuous
exercise so you have cardiovascular
because you're lifting
But shoveling snow is high
intensity. It's isometric.
You're lifting heavy snow.
So it's a weight training
exercise that's putting
an afterload onto your
heart. So now you have kind
of like this perfect storm
of everything happening
at once with isometric and
anybody who has any kind of
underlying condition, it's
going to show and it's going
to come out during this
event. And it also increases
your risk of blood clots
due to the fact that you
have less viscous blood.
So a snowstorm with somebody
shoveling is just, it's
like exactly what I just
said. It's the perfect storm.
And when you go to lift
that snow, you're also
performing a valsalva maneuver
where you're holding your
breath, which is also a
strain, which is why you always
see. And we typically
shovel snow in the morning.
So in the morning, our
cortisol is higher and our
vessels are much more
constricted also. so you have
multiple risk factors that
occur during that so please if
there's anything that you
stress with your patients
it's do not get out and shovel
snow if you are not sure
if your cardiovascular
condition so lastly I'm going
to talk about altitude
training because this is um
I think a lot of people
misinterpret this so what
happens when you go to
high altitude specifically
most changes occur above
3900 feet so what happens
at this level is the air
pressure drops the amount
of oxygen in the air it
never changes it's the
bariatric air pressure that
changes which means there's
less oxygen available for
our bodies to use so when
we go to a high altitude
location immediately our
bodies try to compensate
and by the way there's a
reason our Olympic Training
Center is in Colorado.
It's right next to Pikes Peak.
And there's a reason for this
because it's an excellent
place to train, to adapt
your body to training.
If we're not used to altitude,
what we originally see
with this before we, I know
you've probably learned
about altitude sickness,
but what happens is you
get a rise in heart rate,
which if our heart rate's
increasing, our ventilation's
increasing. So it's almost
like a hyperventilator,
you're breathing faster
you know your heart is
pumping harder because we have
to get oxygen out to the
working muscles your stroke
volume or the amount of
blood that's being pumped or
beat it doesn't change
because there's no reason to
change your stroke volume
but what does change is
the chemistry in our blood
because we're breathing out
and excelling we're expelling
so much carbon dioxide
and breathing so fast the
blood becomes more alkaline
remember what i said
about increasing hydrogen
ions and we can't, we blow
out a lot of carbon dioxide
to get rid of that
alkalinity, to get rid of the
hydrogen ions. So what
happens is we're always almost
in this anaerobic state and
we fatigue much quicker.
Now, if we stay at this
altitude for 10 to 14 days,
we'll adapt. And it's quite
amazing that our bodies
start adapting. We start to
create more red blood cells,
which carries more oxygen
to the tiny little blood
vessels that we have and we
even build more mitochondria
in our muscles to make
us more efficient and we
come better at using fat
as fuel so we spare some of
the muscle glycogen because
we're not in that anaerobic
state anymore so it's a
huge huge huge win for
endurance athletes to train
at these high altitudes but
keep in mind these these
are because they start to
fade within a month of
coming back to sea level so
when you have sports teams
that are going from these low
levels to these high levels
it truly is a disadvantage
they are some really cool
things now in our area
where you um you can go
and train in rooms that are
at high altitude barometric
pressure but you'd have
to do it it the reason it
doesn't work as well is because
we're not in it all the
time so they do it but
it's this there's a lack
of research really on it um
and the key thing with this
hydration as well because
we're at this altitude and
not used to it and you're
breathing more, you sweat
more because it's dry air.
Remember I said you
don't sweat enough when
it's high humidity. So our
core temperature rises when
it's really hot and humid.
Well, when it's dry air,
it's the opposite. We sweat
more. So water intake
becomes absolutely crucial,
which is why you always see
humidifiers. If you're going
into any place that has
an eye altitude, you ask
for a humidifier in your
room and always drink water.
You can't drink enough water
if you're first getting there.
Obviously, the highest
summit that we have
is Mount Everest, which
is about 29,000 feet.
Keep in mind, air is
always 20.9% oxygen, but
the barometric pressure
there is really, really,
really, really different
and low. So I think the
oxygen saturation below
70%, which is why when
most people climb up
there, they require oxygen.
So the real takeaway with
this is that if you are
someone who runs regularly,
exercise regularly, and
you go to high altitude,
do not expect the same
response that you get here.
You are not deconditioned.
And if you are a physician
from here that is
going to work out in
high altitudes or race
high in altitudes, these
are all things to look
for when you see these
altitude changes. so
lastly my last three minutes
that I have you and I know
I kept you for an hour
and I promise you could
probably pause it here and
I'll go really quick if not is
what we expect from adaptation
adaptation from exercise
is the fit principle VP
this is an exercise science
look at this as if you were
prescribing medicine you
wouldn't just hand somebody
a blood pressure pill and
say I don't know take any
dose you want once a month
and hopefully you'll reduce
your blood pressure it's
the same concept here the
frequency how it's done how
intense you're doing it the
time how long you're doing
it the type of modality
all plays a role in how we
train our individual patients
and then of course there's
the volume and progression
that comes with that all
this is true for an athlete
all this is true for somebody
recovering from surgery
anybody from cardiac rehab
some of my best moments were
working in cardiac rehab
because you see people
who are really scared into
losing their function in
their life, and you watch
how they bounce back from
that. It's really quite
remarkable the change you
can make in someone's life.
These are your
physiological adaptations
that occur, okay? We
know that you increase
mitochondria, capitalization,
plasma volume.
Know all these changes, but
understand how long they take.
Okay.
I'm going to just tell you,
I will go to the next slide.
Please understand this
side. These are the
cardiac adaptations from
endurance and strain
training that happen.
Okay. In your cardiac.
I don't want to read them
to you. I just want you to
understand what happened.
It's everything we've
spoken about, but it's all
kind of put into this little
chart of what happens
during training and all this
does happen with training
that being said here's your
cardiovascular and pulmonary
adaptations not much
different than was on the
screen I'm just keeping it
on here to keep reminding
you to understand what these
adaptations are lastly how
do we adapt to exercise
and how long this is the
time difference and the
only thing I could tell you
is if you're looking to do
research and I see this
with a lot of people they
were like oh we're going
to do strength training for
four weeks and see if we
see any changes well this is
how long it takes to see
the adaptations to these
cardiovascular changes and
this is how long it takes
with strength training
so we start to see neural
adaptations in about two to
three weeks and then we see
high intensity training like
about three to five weeks
but we don't see muscle
hypertrophy in four to six
weeks so you really need
to make sure if you're
looking at changes even in
yourself when you say i don't
see anything i'm not getting
stronger we'll really
understand that it takes
at least six weeks for any
kind of changes to really
take part in any of this.
In closing, there are a
lot of slides after this
that you're not going to
hear me on because I went
over my one hour marker
and I do apologize for you.
Most adults do not hit
activity guidelines. I
did not give you the
activity guidelines because
I feel like any kind of
improvement in movement
is acceptable to anybody.
I'm not going to tell someone
to exercise 150 minutes
per week if it's not
conducive to who i'm dealing
with please treat everybody
very individual when it
comes to exercise science um
i'm sorry i didn't we did
not get to go to muscle type
and all of that and that
will be in another lecture
so please don't feel like
we kind of just avoided all
the muscle type and fiber
type there are a lot of
slides after this that again
i won't speak of but i do
We want you to understand
fully the contraindications
to exercise and also to
stopping an exercise test.
And the rest are just
practice samples for you to
read to help you with
your exam. So thank you.
Please feel free to email
me with any questions.